# Alessandro Pezzato

· SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER @ STANDARD AI

Trebaseleghe, PD, Italy

💌 alessandro@pezzato.net | 👑 1986 | 🛠 alepez.dev | 🖸 alepez | 🤡 alessandro-pezzato | 🛅 alessandropezzato

"Learn. Code. Teach. Repeat."

# Summary.

With 19+ years of **software development** experience and a passion for programming since age 11, I bring extensive expertise. Specializing in **C++** since 2007 and **Rust** since 2018, I consistently deliver high-quality solutions. I offer consulting, training, and software development services in **Rust**, **C**, **C++**, **Linux**, and technologies for **embedded** and IoT systems. From 2014 to September 2024, I worked as an **independent software consultant**, taking on various projects. As a **trainer**, I've organized and conducted numerous Rust and C++ **courses**, sharing best practices and methodologies. Since September 2024, I have been working as a **Senior Software Engineer** at **StandardAI**, focusing primarily on **Rust**.

# Work Experience (employee) \_\_\_\_\_

#### Standard Al · Senior Software Engineer, Rust

San Francisco, California (Remote) (Sep 2024 - Present)

- Maintained and enhanced tracking software written in Rust for monitoring people's movement within large retail stores, utilizing AI for person recognition.
- Implemented new features and tracking algorithms to optimize hardware and cloud costs.
- Maintained company core libraries in Rust
- Assisted less experienced colleagues in solving their issues with the Rust language.
- Mentored new colleagues with little or no experience in Rust.
- Conducted code reviews
- Integrated ML models into Rust software.
- Actively participated in discussions on the architecture of new software.
- Achieved a significant reduction in costs by completing a new tracking software that requires only one-third of the cameras compared to the
  previous version.

# Work Experience (as independent consultant) \_\_\_

#### Qascom S.r.l. · TRAINER

Bassano del Grappa, Italy (2021, 2024)

- Organized a 45 hours C++ course for 20 developers working on GNSS and space cybersecurity systems (2021)
- Organized two courses of advanced C++, for a total of 25 developers and 120 hours of lessons. (2024)

#### **Bluewind S.r.l.** • Developer, Consultant, Trainer

Castelfranco Veneto, Italy (2018 - 2024)

- Implemented drivers and firmware for safety critical embedded systems for automotive, marine and industrial products. C, C++, Rust.
- Organized C++ and Rust courses for about ten developers.
- Active member in a working group dedicated to create an open-source peripheral access crate for Infineon microcontrollers. Developed low level Rust drivers for Infineon TC37x microcontrollers. (2023 2024)

### Fracarro Radioindustrie S.r.l. · Developer, Consultant, Trainer

Castelfranco Veneto, Italy (2023 - 2024)

- Organized an 80 hours Advanced C++ course for 4 developers.
- Worked on the modernization of a C codebase, converting some parts to C++ and introducing unit tests, CI/CD and static analysis tools.

## Fiam Utensili Pneumatici S.p.A. · Consultant

Vicenza, Italy (2023)

• I conducted code reviews in various C and C++ projects (PIC, STM32, Windows) to assess their needs for bug fixes, documentation, and maintainability. To facilitate the smooth transition of a resigning team member, I provided consultancy services to help documentating the code.

#### **Texa S.p.A.** • Developer, Consultant, Trainer

Monastier, Italy (2014 - 2023)

- Developed C++ communication libraries (both embedded and server side) for an IoT automotive project to handle real-time remote diagnostic data of about 500 thousands vehicles.
- Organized multiple C++ courses between 2015 and 2022, a total of about 150 hours and 40 developers.

#### **Spring Tech Innovations S.r.l.** Developer, Consultant

Limena, Italy (2022)

• Developed C++ software for an home automation and alarm system. Qt, LVGL, Linux.

### Ferrous Systems GmbH · DEVELOPER

Berlin, Germany (2022)

• Developed Rust compiler tests for Ferrocene qualified toolchain.

#### **MERMEC S.p.A.** · Developer, Consultant

*Morgano, Italy (2020 - 2022)* 

• Developed C++ and C# software for surface inspection of steel products.

#### ASTRA Yacht S.r.l. · Developer, Consultant

Monfalcone, Italy (2015 - 2022)

• Developed C++ software for sailboat real-time performance analysis and firwmare for data collection from the boat sensors. FreeRTOS, Azure RTOS, Linux, Qt, NMEA2000, CAN bus.

#### Salvagnini S.p.A. · TRAINER

Sarego, Italy (2019 - 2020)

- Organized a course on modern C++ and Test Driven Development, for a total of 24 hours and 10 developers.
- Organized a course on Test Driven Development for C and C++, for a total of 24 hours and 10 developers.

#### **Ubilot S.r.l.** • Developer, Consultant

Bassano del Grappa, Italy (2019)

• Developed C++ and C# software. I developed an high-reliability embedded database built on top of a F-RAM module with some kB of storage.

Adatta S.r.l. · TRAINER

Padova, Italy (2018)

· Coached a junior C++ developer.

Carel S.p.A. · Developer, Consultant

Brugine, Italy (2014 - 2018)

Developed C++ software and C Linux drivers for HVAC products. Buildroot, Yocto, Linux.

#### **GM Trading srls** · Developer

**Borgoricco**, *Italy* (2014 - 2018)

• Developed UI of an e-commerce website (JavaScript)

# Work Experience (employee) \_\_\_

#### Vimage S.r.l. · Lead Software Developer

*Mirano, Italy* (Jul 2007 - Jul 2014)

- Coordinated and mentored the R&D team of up to 5 developers.
- · Worked on different projects for museums, stores and events. Most projects involved interactive projections, touchscreens, touchless sensors
- Developed company's core C++ libraries for 2d and 3d games. (OGRE, Chipmunk, Open Dynamics Engine)
- Developed company's core C++ libraries for computer vision. (OpenCV, Point Cloud Library)
- Developed a company Linux distribution based on Gentoo Linux.

#### Nasch S.r.l. · WEB DEVELOPER

Padova, Italy (Oct 2005 - Apr 2007)

- Developed local companies websites (PHP and JavaScript).
- Developed a web tv platform (Flash and ActionScript 3)

# Education

Liceo Scientifico E. Majorana · Scientific High school diploma with a specialization in

Mirano, Italy (2001 - 2005)

THE NATIONAL INFORMATICS PLAN (P.N.I.)

Padua, Italy (2005 - 2006)

Università di Padova · Mechanical Engineering (Incomplete)

Venice, Italy (2006 - 2008)

Università Ca' Foscari Venezia · Business Administration (Incomplete)

## Skills

Programming tools and techniques Git, gdb, Docker, NeoVim, CLion, TDD, CI, GitLab, GitHub, Agile, Design Patterns

**Programming Languages** C++, C, Rust, TypeScript, Python, Haskell, C#, Bash

Languages Italian, English

# Non-profit

### CodingGym · TRAINER

www.coding-gym.org (Feb. 2018 - Present)

- · Conducted monthly free workshops, in Padova and Castelfranco Veneto, assisting over 100 participants
- Designed exercises covering algorithms, data structures, and problem-solving for monthly workshops

I hereby authorize the use of my personal data in accordance to the GDPR 679/16 - European regulation on the protection of personal data.